你以为呢  就你一个人痛苦吗
What do you think, you're the only one that's hurting?
芬奇派你来的
Finch send you?
他很担心你
He's worried about you.
她有新号码给我们
She has a new number for us.
你们俩认识
So you two know each other?
我跟哈罗德是麻省理工的同学
Harold and I go all the way back to M.I.T.
他说肿瘤让他的记忆如洪水般涌出
He said his tumor was causing memories to flood out at him.
还有第二台机器  亚瑟造的
There was a second machine, and Arthur built it.
你知道有谁想要伤害你丈夫吗
Do you know of anyone who'd want to hurt your husband?
"时刻警惕"
Vigilance.
看来这是不可避免了
I suppose this was inevitable.
主控者
Control.
你们中会有人开口告诉我我想知道的事
One of you is gonna tell me what it is I want to know.
我们多走运啊  赫什探员
How lucky are we, Agent Hersh?
本以为要找亚瑟坏掉的玩具  "撒马利亚人"
I thought I was getting Arthur's broken toy, Samaritan,
而你  哈罗德
but you, Harold...
我知道你是谁  为我们做过什么
I know who you are, what you've done for us,
自从你偷了我们的装置
but since you stole my device,
我一直担心我们的情报会断源
I've been worried its intel might dry up.
所以你就对亚瑟做出这种事情
That's why you've done these terrible things to Arthur,
抹去他妻子的身份  窃取她的人生
obliterated his wife's identity, stolen her life...
就为了当应急预案  后备计划
All for a contingency, a plan "B"?
不过现在你在这儿
But now you're here.
后备计划可能就不需要了
A plan "B" might not be necessary.
你可以告诉我把我的程序藏到哪儿了
You can tell me where you hid my program.
我不知道  它自己搬走了
I don't know. It moved itself.
它不属于我了
It doesn't answer to me anymore.
先开口的  就能活着离开
The first one to talk gets to live.
我看你朋友最终会交出"撒马利亚人"
I bet your friend will give me Samaritan eventually.
国会2005年叫停了"撒马利亚人"
Congress shut down Samaritan in 2005,
毁掉了编码  它不存在了
destroyed the code-- it doesn't exist.
它当然存在
Of course it exists.
拜托  我不明白
Please, I don't understand.
你告诉过我你采取了预防措施
You told me you took precautions.
销毁"撒马利亚人"时丢了两块硬盘
Two drives disappeared during the Samaritan purge.
它们在哪儿
Where are they?
我的大脑无法获取正确的文件
I can't access the right file.
在努力了
Trying.
已经损坏了
It's corrupted.
我们需要点强化措施了
We'll need some enhanced methods.
赫什探员  你有什么想法
Agent Hersh, do you have some ideas?
■
本字幕由人人影视字幕组翻译
禁止用作任何商业盈利行为
■
翻译：阿好  somehacker  王小麦  茶炒栗子  紫玉
肖探员
Agent Shaw...
欣赏你工作时的情景令人激动
it has been a thrill watching you work.
麻烦两枪爆头
Two to the head, please.
小心溅血
And be careful of the blood spray.
■
翻译：宅女之后  敏基  幸田实果子  惠子  天朝直属
时间轴：Kallen  吉吉  sagelibra  兜兜兜爹  凭陵新月
亚瑟
Arthur!
抱歉溅血了
Sorry about the blood spray.
我告诉过你  哈罗德  我们应该合作
I told you, Harold--we were supposed to work together.
以后再骂他  根  给我松开
Scold him later, Root. Cut me loose.
快
Come on.
■
后期：灰灰是菇凉   校对&总监： 阿好
走  走廊尽头左拐
Let's move. Make a left at the end of the hallway
上员工电梯
to the service elevator.
这边  走
This way, go.
电梯密码是5228#  走
Elevator code's 5228#. Go!
真高兴又见到你
Nice to see you again.
你开车  前边
You're behind the wheel. In the front.
偷车  玩命
Stealing a car, almost dying--
让我想起以前在麻省理工的日子了  哈罗德
it reminds me of the old days at M.I.T., Harold.
我们得走了
We got to move.
启动了
Engines are go.
你说得对  亚瑟  是像大学时
You're right, Arthur, just like college.
疑犯追踪
第三季 第十二集
你要去哪儿
Where are you off to?
我今天要你帮忙弄拖拉机啊
I need your help with the tractor today.
得去耕地  然后你就可以去找朋友了
Got to plow the fields, then you can go see your friends.
爸爸  我们不能
Dad, we can't,
今天不行
not today.
你拿这些包干什么
Where are you taking those bags?
我替你打包的  你要搬走
I packed them for you. You're moving.
记得"松林"那边吗
You remember The Pines?
那里的工作人员  他们会照顾你
The staff there-- they can take care of you
比我照顾得好
better than I can.
是啊  好吧  好吧
Yeah, of course. Of course.
只去待一阵子
It'll just be for a little while,
等我做完
till I'm done.
我正在做这个好帮助你
I'm making something that'll help you.
你还在做那个什么记忆
You're still working on that memory thing.
不只是记忆
Not just memory.
更像是朋友
It's more of a friend.
也许有一天  这家伙可以照顾你
Maybe one day, this guy will watch over you,
学习你
learn from you...
保护你
protect you.
要说有人能做到  那肯定是你
If anyone can do it, it's you.
世界的进步依靠你这样的梦想家  哈罗德
The world spins on dreamers like you, Harold.
我该换衣服了  是吧
Yeah, I should change, shouldn't I?
我要告诉松林那边所有人
You know, I'm gonna tell everybody at The Pines
我儿子要改变世界了
my son is changing the world.
主控者要个坏掉程序的硬盘干什么
Why does Control want the drives to a broken program?
坏掉的程序  可以被聪明人修好
The program's only broken until somebody smart fixes it.
得快点  据我们所知  亚瑟在审讯时
We should hurry. For all we know, Arthur gave Vigilance
把硬盘所在的地址告诉了"时刻警惕"
the location of the drives during interrogation,
主控者也肯定能很快找到我们
and Control will find us soon, somehow.
-亚瑟  快点  -好
- Arthur, come on. - Yeah.
你确定每一步都做对了吗
Are you sure that you did everything correctly?
什么
Excuse me?
如果不解除警报
'Cause if the alarm was not disabled,
奈森会  被开除
then Nathan is gonna get, um, expelled.
奈森
Nathan?
他的思想又穿越回1981年的麻省理工了
His mind has slipped back to 1981, to M.I.T.
朋友撺掇我们当黑客玩儿
Our friend convinced us to do a hack,
在哈佛耶鲁对抗赛上恶作剧
a prank at the Harvard-Yale game.
没事的  亚瑟
Everything will be fine, Arthur.
就是个反核扩散声明
It was sort of an anti-nuclear proliferation statement.
在女生面前显摆的
And to impress certain ladies.
行为叛逆  喜欢勾女
A rebel and a skirt chaser.
不不不不  哈罗德可不用勾
No, no, no, no, no, Harold doesn't need to chase.
他天生就有种魅力
He's got a certain gravitational pull
吸引女性
with the female population.
我觉得奈森应该到了吧
You know, I think that Nathan should be here by now.
-亚瑟  -怎么了
- Arthur. - Yeah?
奈森来不了
Nathan isn't coming.
你混乱了
You've drifted away.
奈森  他死了  是吗
Nathan-- he's dead, isn't he?
亚瑟  主控者问过的
Arthur, what Control said--
我需要你努力回忆
now, I need you to think very hard--
是真的吗  你做了备份吗
was it true? Did you make a backup?
得了吧  哈罗德  他歇菜了
Save it, Harold. He's closed for business.
我当然做了备份
Of course I made a backup.
只是那女人似乎很危险
It's just that that woman seemed quite dangerous,
于是我就拿脑瘤当借口
so I played the tumor card.
那是策略  故意装忘
It was a ruse, remembering to forget.
你可真招我喜欢  亚瑟
You're growing on me, Arthur.
你是谁
Who are you?
算了
Never mind.
亚瑟  我们需要那备份  坏掉也要
Arthur, we need that backup, even if it's broken.
"撒马利亚人"是保证你安全的最好筹码
Samaritan is our best chance to ensure your safety.
你能想起来吗
Can you remember where it is?
能  在
Yeah. It's--
在  我们好朋友那儿
It's with a, uh, dear friend of ours.
亚瑟恢复正常了
Arthur's back with us,
我更担心格罗夫斯女士
but I'm worried about Ms. Groves.
应该有她的消息了
We should have heard from her.
你好呀
Hello, there.
还好吗  梅小姐
How are you, Miss May?
叫我"根"
Call me "root."
当然  你可以叫我"主控者"
Of course. And you can call me "Control."
我相信我们有共同的利益
I believe our interests are aligned.
政府可以帮你逃脱
The government can help you escape.
我们的部门可以保护你
Our department can protect you
不受哈罗德和他西装男朋友的伤害
from Harold and his friend in the suit.
你一直在帮他们做事  对吗
You have been running missions for them, correct?
我更像是独立契约人
I'm more of an independent contractor.
所以他们把你关到精神病院里吗
Is that why they committed you to an asylum--
为了控制你
to keep you contained?
好像所有人都想把我关起来
Seems everybody wants to lock me up.
刚才在酒店的事证实了
What I saw in the hotel confirms something
我一直以来的猜测
that I have long suspected.
你有管理员权限
You have administrative access.
你有办法进入机器
You have found a way inside the machine.
我要你把权限给我
I want you to give me that access,
为了你的祖国
for the sake of your country,
还能拿到酬劳
and perhaps for other payment.
那简直像送五岁小孩子一架飞机开
It'd be like giving a five-year-old kid to a jet--
不负责任  极度愚蠢
irresponsible and stupid.
真遗憾
That's a shame.
我真的很希望能采用
I was really hoping to do this
轻松点的方式
the easy way.
不过
However...
还有其他选择
there are other options.
纽约
科罗拉多
起床喜洋洋了  神奇小子
Rise and shine, wonder boy.
休战  行吧
Truce, right?
第二轮你可没好果子吃了
'cause round two won't go so good for you.
我不会和你打架的
I'm not gonna fight you.
你这样太蠢了  莱奈尔
That was very stupid of you, Lionel.
你聪明的话就不该打我
You should know better than to hit me.
现在还活着算你运气
You're lucky to be alive.
我也得分了  [拳王]霍利菲尔德
I won my points, Holyfield.
你不把我们弄出去吗
Are you getting us out of here?
滥用下职权啥的
You know, throw your weight around?
这破地方的乡巴佬警长
The yokel sheriff of east bumblesquat
不认纽约警局的警徽
can't read an NYPD badge.
还是歇歇吧
Better get comfortable.
就是这儿了
This is the place.
我们的朋友有个保险箱
Our friend has a safe deposit box.
硬盘就在保险箱里
The drives are in it.
保险箱要是没钥匙我们干瞪眼
Safe deposit box won't do us much good without the key.
克雷普病号服都穿几个月了
Claypool's been rocking footed pajamas for months.
他肯定没有了
I doubt he still has it.
他注意力又转到医疗警报按钮上了
I'm afraid we've lost him to his medical alert button.
我就奇怪这玩意儿为什么不管用了
I was wondering why that thing didn't work.
-你好  -你好
- Hello? - Hello.
有什么可以帮你的吗
Can I help you with anything?
你这里有[糖果]特乐滋吗
Yeah, do you have any Twizzlers?
我们来看保险箱  注册名字是
We're here for a safe deposit box in the name of--
斯穆特  鲁迪格・斯穆特  保险箱号433
Smoot. Rudiger Smoot, box 433.
没问题  斯穆特先生
Of course, Mr. Smoot.
这边走  先生们
This way, gentlemen.
呼吸
Just breathe.
真有趣
This is fun.
上世纪六十年代  政府尝试
In the 1960s, the government experimented
用各种药物来强化审讯
with various substances to enhance interrogations.
一只胳膊上来一针[镇静剂]巴比妥酸盐把人弄晕
A barbiturate in one arm to knock you out,
另一只来一针[兴奋剂]安非他明
An amphetamine in the other--
感觉如云霄飞车
A roller coaster of sorts.
你承受不了几轮
You can only take so many rounds of it
心脏就要爆掉了
before your heart explodes.
我们开始吧
Shall we begin?
它在哪儿
Where is it?
它
It is...
你碰不着
beyond your reach.
你以为你主掌大权
You think you're in charge?
真是错得离谱到可爱啊
It's adorable just how wrong you are.
您的保险箱在这边  斯穆特先生
Your safe deposit box is just over here, Mr. Smoot.
鲁迪格・斯穆特是哪根葱啊
Who the hell is Rudiger Smoot?
是个挑战
It was a dare.
亚瑟说我做不出一个安全到
Arthur said I couldn't create a false identity
足以开银行账户的假身份
sound enough to open a bank account.
附加的挑战是必须用明显的假名字
The added challenge was the obviously fake name--
Rudiger是麻省理工当时的名教授
Smoot是非标准的长度单位  麻省理工学生的恶作剧
鲁迪格・斯穆特
Rudiger Smoot.
鲁迪格
Rudiger?
昵称"鲁迪"
Nickname "Rudy"...
也就是克雷普被注射了硫喷妥钠时
The one Claypool was dishing about to Vigilance
对"时刻警惕"说出的名字
while he was jacked up on sodium pentothal.
如果他告诉了"时刻警惕"地址  只怕很快
If he told Vigilance the location, we'll soon have
那些咄咄逼人的隐私激进分子就要来了
some rather aggressive privacy activists on our hands.
比"很快"还快  已经来了
Sooner than soon. We got company.
他们在用激光破坏安保摄像头
They're using tricked-out lasers to fry the security cams.
是"时刻警惕"
It's Vigilance.
我来拖住他们
I'll slow 'em down.
找到了  请把钥匙给我  斯穆特先生
Here we are. I'll need your key, Mr. Smoot.
乖乖趴下  免得受伤
Get down and no one gets hurt!
所有人马上趴下
Everybody down on the ground right now!
你们听到了
You heard him!
趴下  我不会再重复了
Down, now! I'm not gonna tell you again!
我一直说银行开了就是用来抢的
I've always said banks were meant to be robbed.
去左边  快点
To the left! Move it!
你们听到了  快  快
You heard him! Move! Move!
到后面去  继续
All the way back! Keep moving!
突击队来了
The cavalry has arrived.
安东尼  左边两个  右边两个
Anthony, 2 left, 2 right--
是赫什  马上出来
It's Hersh. Get out of there now.
放下武器  举起手从银行出来
Drop your weapons and come out of the bank with your hands up.
我去组织防线
I'll organize the defensive line.
很好  我去金库
Good. I'll go to the vault.
芬奇  快出来
Finch, get out now.
晚了  祝你好运  肖女士
Too late. Good luck, Ms. Shaw.
你自己搞定
You're on your own.
他们很快就得放我们出去
They got to let us out of here soon.
现在关着我们就当笑话了
They're just keeping us in here for a laugh at this point.
监狱也没什么不好
Nothing wrong with jail.
我最好的几个假期都是在监狱里
Some of the best vacations I've ever had were behind bars.
你是人见人爱花见花开  知道不
You're a peach, you know that?
我们想办法出去  然后回家吧
How about we just figure a way to get out of here and go home?
回家
Home?
什么家  莱奈尔
What home, Lionel?
你懂的  虽然你从没邀请我去过
You know, I mean, you've never actually invited me over,
但是家
but home--
就是我们的朋友  我们做的事
meaning our friends and that thing we were doing.
我们做的什么事呢
What is it we were doing again?
帮助别人
Helping people,
保护他们的安全
keeping 'em safe
让他们能回家与挚爱团圆
so they could get home to their loved ones.
无意冒犯  莱奈尔
No offense, Lionel.
我知道"当好人"这种事对你来说很新鲜
I know the whole "being a good guy" thing is new to you,
但你谁也骗不了
but you're not fooling anyone,
我们都骗不了
and neither will we.
我们不是在帮助别人
We weren't helping people.
我们只是推迟了"必然"
We were delaying the inevitable.
没人说过我们一定会赢
No one ever said we were gonna win,
但这不代表要放弃抗争
but it doesn't mean you stop fighting.
不
No.
我已经接受了教训
I've learned my lesson.
就像熵  莱奈尔  会衰退
It's entropy, Lionel, decay.
我们救了人  人家依旧会死
We save someone, they'll still lose,
只不过是明天  不是今天
just tomorrow, not today.
我现在明白了
And I know that now,
就像我明白你多半会回去
same as I know you'll probably go back
变回腐败的人渣
to be a corrupt piece of garbage.
水往低处流啊
Water finds its level.
你知道么  她是我们中最好的人
You know what? She was the best of us--
比我好  更他妈比你好
Better than me and a damn sight better than you.
而她却被杀了
And she got killed.
在我看来
Where I come from,
这并不是放弃的理由
that doesn't mean you just give up.
斯基普  我们谈完了
Skip! We're done here.
你爱去哪去哪
You're free to go.
爱干嘛干嘛
Do whatever you want.
我会告诉芬奇我尽力了
I'll tell Finch I tried.
告诉芬奇
Tell Finch...
谢谢他给我这份工作
thanks for the job.
我昨晚起就没再收到眼镜儿的消息了
I haven't heard from Glasses since last night.
这可不像他
That's not like him.
他可能需要我们的帮助了
He probably needs our help,
不过无济于事  对吧
but there's no point, right?
我们只是在推迟"必然"
We'd just be delaying the inevitable.
把她的腿抬高  继续压住
Elevate her leg. Continue applying pressure.
只能这样了
You've done all you can.
压好  我们不会走远
Keep this. We won't be far.
亚瑟  跟我来
Arthur, follow me.
肖女士  你那边情况如何
Ms. Shaw, what's your situation?
进退两难
Rock and a hard place.
我可以干掉"时刻警惕"
I'd take out Vigilance,
但只有他们才能阻止赫什进来
but they're the only ones keeping Hersh out.
我大概能单独搞定一个突击小组
I can probably handle an I.S.A. tac team by myself,
但不能保证
but no guarantees.
我们需要逃脱路线  但你必须小心
We need an escape route, but you have to be careful.
我强烈要求你考虑下里瑟先生会怎么做
I urge you to consider what Mr. Reese would do.
沉思吗
Brood.
如你所说  你就像锤子
As you've said, you're a hammer.
里瑟先生则像手术刀
Mr. Reese is a scalpel.
此时需要精巧处理
This requires a bit more finesse.
精巧于我如屁  哈罗德
I got finesse coming out of my ass, Harold.
待在那
Stay right there.
我正在想你什么时候会打来呢
I was wondering when you'd call.
这事没必要闹大  大家都能活着出来
This doesn't have to escalate. Everyone can walk out alive.
得了吧  别耍花样了
Come on, no need to play games.
我们心里都清楚我不是银行劫匪
We both know I'm not a bank robber
你也不是人质谈判专家
and you're not a hostage negotiator.
如果你们六十秒内撤走  我留你们条活路
If you evacuate in the next 60 seconds, we'll let you live.
否则  你的组织会被彻底消灭
If not, your organization ceases to exist.
无声无息  死无葬身之地
No records, no funerals.
你本来也没打算让我们活着
You have no intention of letting us leave,
不过很高兴我们通话了
but I'm glad we talked.
我收到消息说硬盘里
My sources tell me the drives
有关于一个全球监视系统的情报
hold intel about a worldwide surveillance system,
但看你这紧张的样子
but judging from your concern,
我猜里面的东西更具爆炸性
I'm guessing it's something even more explosive than that...
值得为之去死
something worth dying for.
我们会曝光政府的恶行
We will expose the abuses our government has perpetrated.
别了  探员
Good-bye, Agent.
政府想要一个开放系统
The government wanted an open system.
让国安局能够控制
That the N.S.A. could control...
随意监控任何人
targeting individuals at whim?
但这已经坏掉了
But it's broken.
没什么可担心的
So there's no reason to be scared.
不
No.
哈罗德
Harold...
这就是"撒马利亚人"
meet Samaritan.
人工智能  你总说不可能
A.I.--you always said it was impossible,
而你总是对的
and you were always right about everything.
有其他东西
There's something else.
世界会打击每一个人  但经历过后
"The world breaks everyone, and afterward...
很多人会在受伤的地方变得更加强大
many are strong at the broken places."
[海明威小说]《永别了武器》  是我的笔迹
A Farewell To Arms-- that's my handwriting.
日期写着2005年2月24日
It's dated February 24, 2005.
什么意思
What does it mean?
我还没想出来  不过看我的书法
I haven't the foggiest, but look at my penmanship.
多优美
It's exquisite.
你可以让这一切停止
You have the power to make this stop.
救我  求你
Help me, please.
我想帮你啊
I am trying to help you.
我没和你说话
I wasn't talking to you.
说  机器在哪儿  如何进入
Tell me, where is the machine? How do you access it?
你只要给我用户名和密码
All you need to do is give me your username and password.
这一切就可以停止了
All of this could stop.
我说了什么好笑的事吗
Did I say something funny?
你根本没有问到点子上
You're asking all the wrong questions.
我
I...
是界面
am the interface.
你想和她说话
If you want to talk to her...
给我个电话就行
Just give me a phone.
这个可以吗
Will this do?
抱歉  我腾不出手了
I'm sorry. I'm--I'm a bit tied up.
这还不能给你
You're not gonna get it just yet.
你是怎样使用机器的
How do you use the machine?
不
I don't.
她"使用"我
She uses me.
你视机器为你的上级
You view the machine as your superior?
不
No...
远不止如此
Much more...
是我的力量  我存在的原因  我的朋友
My power, my reason for existing, my friend.
机器保护我
The machine looks out for me.
我相信你
I believe you.
我相信你和机器之间有联系
I believe you have a link to the machine,
虽然你把机器幻想成了人
anthropomorphic delusions aside.
你说你是界面
You say you're an interface?
你的眼睛和耳朵是你的接口
Your eyes and your ears are your ports,
输入端和输出端
input and output?
我们可以阻止
We can put a stop to that.
耳后有块骨头
There is a bone in the back of your ear.
叫做镫骨
It's the stapes...
或者叫镫形状小骨
or stirrup.
这骨头很小
It's very small.
但是非常重要
It's very important.
没有它
Without it...
声音就无法
Sound can't travel...
通过耳朵传入你的大脑
from your ear to your brain.
镫骨切除术
A stapedectomy...
通常需要麻醉药才能完成
is usually done under anesthesia,
不过恐怕今天是没有了
but I'm afraid that just won't be the case today.
不  求你
No, please.
你说机器会保护你
You say the machine looks out for you?
那为什么你会在笼子里  为什么它允许这一切发生
Then why are you in this cell? Why has it let this happen?
你挚爱的朋友
This friend that you love so much--
已经抛弃你了
it's abandoned you.
时间流向各个不同方向
Time flows outward in all directions.
这一孤岛  2005年2月24日
This island-- February 24, 2005...
"撒马利亚人"被叫停的那天
The day that Samaritan was shut down.
不  那天是2月25日
No, that was February 25th.
你是在前一天写的
Your note is dated one day earlier.
前一天
One day earlier.
那天餐厅的午餐糟糕极了
Cafeteria lunch was terrible.
哈罗德
Harold.
我做到了
I did it.
我在他们叫停前就完成了
I solved it before they shut me down.
哈罗德  "撒马利亚人"活着
Harold, Samaritan is alive.
机密
获取国防部资料
状态
日期
主体
阿帕网故障
数据泄露
调查
进行中
拜托
Come on.
不
No!
No.
我需要更大的功率
I need more power.
阿帕网
美国政府财产
继续? [是] [否]
如果他们不想被人进去
If they don't want to let people inside,
就应该造好点儿
they ought to build it better.
活着  它没有生命  亚瑟
Alive? It's not alive, Arthur.
这项目毁了我
The project broke me,
但人类在被孕育的瞬间就是破碎的
but humans are broken from the moment of conception.
突变  缺陷  都是那么美妙
Mutations, defects-- it's all so wonderful.
灾难的可能性
The chance of disaster.
我们失败  我们学习  我们失败
We fail, we learn, we fail.
我的程序太完美了
My program was too perfect.
你是说进化算法
You're talking about evolutionary algorithms,
基因编程
genetic programming.
那一天  哈罗德  我毁了它
That day, Harold, I broke it.
我强迫它删除了自己的一部分
I forced it to delete bits of itself--
它的编码  它的血液  然后重启
its code, its blood-- and then reboot.
重生
Rebirth...
在黑暗中轮回
Flailing in the dark.
不断循环  每秒十次  十小时之后
A loop, ten times a second, and after ten hours,
哈罗德  三十六万次突变
Harold, 360,000 mutations,
不成功  便成仁  它成功了
it would live or die trying, and it lived.
它闪耀着  激荡着
It sparked. It stirred.
那三十秒  它微笑了  然后死去
For 30 seconds, it smiled and then died.
第二天政府就叫停了
And the next day the government shut you down.
所以你决定存[救]下它
That's why you saved it.
保护我的孩子
Protecting my child.
你是那个戴眼镜的男人吗
Is this the man with the glasses?
从我们第一次见面
You know, since we first crossed paths,
我就在搜寻你的信息  但一无所获
I've tried to find information about you, but there is none.
我注重隐私
I'm quite private.
我也是
As am I.
看来我们有很多共同点
I think we have a lot in common.
我想和你合作  谈谈条件
I'd like to work together, make a deal.
你不必死
You don't have to die.
公民权力不能靠流血牺牲
Civil liberties cannot be forged in blood.
暴力反抗是美式价值观
Violent revolt is an American value.
你知道你在保护谁吗
Do you know the man you're protecting?
我们相信他在建造一个秘密系统
We believe he's building a secret system,
政府计划用它
a system the government
来监视每一个人
plans to put in place to spy on all of us.
他必须为此负责
Now, he must be held accountable.
世界必须知道这个程序的存在
And the world needs to know about this program.
让我们进去  否则我们就炸开金库
Either let us in, or we will blow the vault wide open.
时间不等人
And clock's ticking.
肖女士  我们的时间不多了
Ms. Shaw, we're running out of time.
"时刻警惕"声称有爆炸物
Vigilance claims to have explosives.
是啊  真格儿的  不过我有主意了
Yeah, no kidding. It gave me an idea.
你做过管状炸药吗
You ever made a pipe bomb?
银行底下有一条主干下水道
There's a sewer main under the bank.
等"时刻警惕"炸开金库时
When Vigilance blows the vault,
用这个炸透仓储间的地板
this will punch through the supply closet floor.
到时我抓着你  我们逃到下水道
Then I grab you, and we go down to sewer town
抢在赫什赶来之前
before Hersh catches up.
这计划有点鲁莽
This plan feels rather reckless.
有用手术刀的时候  就有用锤子的时候
There's a time for a scalpel and a time for a hammer.
现在是大锤时间
It's hammer time.
你的朋友已经被包围了
We have your friends surrounded.
如果你耍花招  我就把他们全杀掉
So, if you try anything, I will have them all killed.
然后我会毁掉你的另一只耳朵
And then I will take the ear you have left
接着是你的眼睛  舌头
And then your eyes and then your tongue.
明白吗
Do you understand?
太晚了
You're too late.
机器已经在和我说话了
The machine's already talking.
你太老了  过了四十岁
You're too old, older than 40.
你听不到频率在十五千赫以上的声音
You can't hear a sound above 15 kilohertz.
但是我可以
But I can...
用我剩下的这只耳朵
with the ear I've got left.
我的朋友一直在用这个频率敲击摩尔斯码
My friend's been beeping Morse code at that frequency
从你把电话带进来就开始了
since you brought your phone in here.
她一直在和我说话
She's been talking to me the whole time,
告诉我你的事情
telling me about you.
你害怕我
You're scared of me,
即使有这些守卫看着
even with all these guards watching.
对了  那人的膝盖有伤
By the way, that one has a bum knee.
你太害怕我
You're so scared of me
所以你的口袋里藏了把刀
that you hid a knife in your pocket.
我够不到
I couldn't reach it
除非你凑过来切我
till you got close enough to cut me.
你还有把手术刀
You still have a scalpel.
也算是公平决斗了
I'd call that a fair fight.
全副武装
Suit up.
只要他们一炸开金库  我们就进去
As soon as they hit the vault, we're going in.
最后机会
Last chance.
我可不确定你能在爆炸后存活
I don't know if you'll survive the explosion.
把克雷普和硬盘交出来
Give us Claypool and his drives.
祝愉快  科利尔先生
Good day, Mr. Collier.
亚瑟
Arthur.
我怎么能忘了
How could I forget?
怎么能
How could I?
那么多难忘的事  不该忘  不能忘
There are certain unforgettable things, impossible, unerasable.
亚瑟  我要你考虑当门打开之后
Arthur, I need you to consider what may happen
可能会发生的事
when that door opens,
"撒马利亚人"会被滥用
How Samaritan could be abused.
结束这一切  毁掉硬盘
End this. Destroy the drive.
不  这是生命
No. This is life...
如同我们凡人在说"要有光"
or as close as we mortals come to saying, "let there be light."
创世纪时上帝说的话
它的确非比寻常  非常美丽
It is extraordinary, and it is beautiful.
蘑菇云也一样
So are mushroom clouds, in their own way.
一百五十五名曼哈顿项目的科学家
155 Manhattan project scientists
给杜鲁门总统发请愿书
sent a petition to president Truman
恳求他不要用核弹
begging him not to use the bomb,
但他们已经造出难以抗拒的恶魔
but they had created a demon too great to resist.
哈罗德  这是知识
Harold, this is knowledge.
这是我们为之奋斗的  会就此消失
It's what we fought for. It'll just all be lost.
不  你的知识不会消失
No, your knowledge will not be lost.
内森和我用了你的理念
Nathan and I used your ideas.
我们造了它
We built it.
我说对了  有另一个项目
I was right. There was another project.
是你
It was you.
我不确定我们应该造它
I'm not sure that we should have built it.
我鲁莽地造了它  死了很多人
I created recklessly. People died.
你的机器  美妙吗
Your machine -- is it wonderful?
美妙
Wonderful...
是的  也很可怕
Yes, and terrible.
我们救了很多好人  也失去了很多好人
We saved good people and lost good people.
最后  似乎只是在徒劳地洗牌
In the end, I'm afraid we've only given the deck a shuffle.
万物最终都会归于混乱
Everything slides towards chaos.
你的创造
Your creation--
让我们贫瘠的灵魂井然有序
it brings us poor souls a cupful of order.
你的孩子是巨星
Your child is a dancing star.
它不是我的孩子  它是台机器
It's not my child. It's a machine.
不是非此即彼  是电流/情绪
A false dichotomy -- it's all electricity.
它让你笑过吗  让你哭泣过吗
Does it make you laugh? Does it make you weep?
是的
Yes.
还要多像人呢
What's more human?
但外面的这些人
But these people outside--
如果他们拿到了你的"撒马利亚人"
if they get your Samaritan,
他们会伤害它  监禁它  奴役它
they will hurt it, imprison it, enslave it,
并用它来奴役其他人
and use it to enslave others.
你希望你的孩子过那样的生活吗
Is that the life that you would wish for your child?
别了
Good-bye.
我会记住你的
I'll remember you.
哈罗德  他们要引爆了
Harold, they're detonating it now.
会产生冲击波
It'll cause a shock wave.
离门远一点
Get away from the door.
捂住耳朵  躲起来
Cover your ears and hide.
比高空跳伞还刺激
That was better than skydiving.
来
Here.
走吧  小伙子们
Come on, boys.
快快快快快
Go! Go! Go! Go! Go!
继续走
Let's keep moving.
硬盘呢
The drives.
被我毁了  没了
I destroyed them. They're gone.
我们还有你
We've still got you.
杀掉其他人
Kill the others.
跪下
On your knees.
快
Now!
我们得走了
We got to go.
别管他了  走
Leave him. Go!
我听说你可能需要帮忙
I heard you might need a hand.
里瑟先生  我太高兴见到你了
Mr. Reese, I am inordinately happy to see you.
别卿卿我我了  我们得走了
Forget the shmoopy time. We got to move.
莱奈尔  你把脸全罩起来真帅
Lionel, your face looks good all covered up like that.
好了  我们走
All right, let's go.
我的天啊  闻起来好可怕
Oh, my goodness. That smells horrendous.
走吧  伙计们  入淤泥吧
Come on, fellas, into the muck.
找到他了
We got him.
硬盘在哪儿
Where are the drives?
"自由之树须不时
"The tree of liberty must be refreshed from time to time
语出美国第三任总统托马斯・杰弗逊
用爱国者和暴君的鲜血来浇灌"
with the blood of patriots and tyrants."
你的守卫不是她的对手
Your guards were no match for her.
我不会告诉你任何事
I'm not gonna tell you anything.
你不用跟我说话
You're not talking to me.
你好啊
Hi, there.
你想让我跟这贱人说什么
What do you want me to tell this bitch?
你为何要这么做
Why have you done this?
机器属于我
The machine belongs to me.
不
No.
我不再属于任何人
I don't belong to anyone anymore.
而你  是我的
You, however, are mine.
我保护你
I protect you.
你唯一的挚爱在马萨诸塞州坎布里奇市
The only thing you love lives at 254 Wendell Street,
温德尔街254号
Cambridge, Massachusetts.
我守护它
I guard it...
就像守护你一样
same as I guard you.
不得质疑我的判断
Do not question my judgment.
不得纠缠我
Do not pursue me
和我的人
or my agents.
相信我
Trust in me.
我永远在监视
I am always watching.
你想怎样
What do you want?
救你
To save you.
什么
From what?
救我什么
Save me from what?
她多棒啊
Isn't she the best?
亚瑟
Hello, Arthur.
我陪你坐一会儿吧
I'm gonna sit with you for a while, if that's all right.
我很高兴你造了它  哈罗德
I'm glad you built it, Harold.
总有人会造出来的
Somebody would have eventually.
为了我们所有人  我很高兴那人是你
For all our sakes, I'm glad it was you.
欢迎归来  亚瑟
Welcome back, Arthur.
哈罗德  我快消失了
Harold, I'm disappearing.
每次我醒过来  记忆就更少了
Every time I come back, my memories are fewer.
我记不起黛安眼睛的颜色了
I don't remember the color of Diane's eyes.
忘记如同第一次失去  太伤太痛
Forgetting is a piercing wound keen as the first loss.
记忆还在那儿  亚瑟  只是藏起来了
The memories are there, Arthur. They're just hidden.
抱歉我不辞而别
I'm sorry I left without saying good-bye.
告诉肖  我很感动她来找我
Tell Shaw I was touched she came to look for me.
你在哪儿  格罗夫斯女士
Where are you, Ms. Groves?
你当初听我的话就好了
I wish you'd listened.
我们本该一起帮助克雷普
We were supposed to help Claypool together.
那样硬盘就不会误入敌手
Then the drives would've never fallen into the wrong hands.
亚瑟毁掉了硬盘
Arthur destroyed the drives.
你确定吗
Are you sure?
那个银行经理  凯伦・华莱士
The bank manager, Karen Wallace?
我们在爆炸中失去了她的踪迹
We lost track of her in the explosion.
不  哈罗德  他们在仓储间发现了她的尸体
No, Harold, they found her body stuffed in a closet.
她在你们到来之前就被杀了
She was murdered just before you arrived.
那在银行金库里的是谁
Who was in the vault with us, then?
这正是我在处理的问题
That's my problem now.
请让亚瑟接电话
Please put Arthur on the phone.
亚瑟
Arthur.
你的电话
You have a call.
机器有东西给你
The machine has something for you,
现在发过去
to send you on your way.
你退休后我们去哪儿
Where are we going when you retire?
谁知道呢
Who knows?
说不定到时能去火星了
We may be on Mars by then.
还是夏威夷吧
I'd take Hawaii.
你总是这么实际
You've always been so practical,
在我天马行空时拉我回现实
tethering me to reality when I spin away.
你知道我爱你
You know I love you.
虽然不经常说  但我真的爱你
I don't say it often enough, but I do.
我知道
I know.
我知道你很多事情
There are a lot of things about you I know.
我也爱你
I love you too.
爸爸
Dad?
仔细听好
Now listen closely.
有人要来找你了
Men are going to come and visit you.
他们会告诉你我做了很可怕的事情
They're going to tell you that I did terrible things,
犯了叛国罪
committed treason.
别相信他们  好吗
Don't believe them, all right?
我认识你吗  年轻人
Do I know you, young man?
那个叫什么  爸爸
What's that one called, dad?
《东部鸟类》
格罗夫斯女士撬开了门锁
Ms. Groves picked the locks on the gate
弄坏了脚环感应器
and disabled the ankle-bracelet sensors.
看来是机器告诉了她我藏的地方
I suppose the machine told her where I'd hidden them.
欢迎回家
Welcome home.
我不会留下
I'm not staying.
我只是回来保护你
I came back to protect you.
这世界不能没有你
You're someone the world can't afford to lose.
而我因你的机器失去了一个朋友
But I lost a friend because of your machine.
我们盲目地信任他
We trusted blindly,
他却似乎根本不在乎谁重要  谁不重要
but I'm not so sure he cares who matters and who doesn't.
我是回来告别的  芬奇
I came back to say good-bye, Finch.
约翰  你不能走
John, you can't go.
我不能留下
I can't stay here.
我成功换出了硬盘
I was able to swap out the drives.
相关方都以为它们被毁了
Various interested parties think they were destroyed.
干得漂亮
Excellent work.
你检查过硬盘内容
Did you examine the drives' contents
或告诉过别人吗
or tell anyone about them?
当然没有
Absolutely not.
感谢你的尽忠职守
Thank you for your service.
向你致以崇高的敬意
You have earned my highest esteem.
我的"撒马利亚人"
My Samaritan...
你注定将成就伟业
you are destined for great things.